# 大家好 今天來看一下家的三華李 熟了沒有
Hi everyone! Today we're gonna take a look at our buddy's Sanhua plums, and see if they are ripe.
# 熟了沒有
Are they ripe?
# 這個
This is,
# 這個楊梅
this bayberry,
# 這是半熟的
it is half-ripe.
# 這個是贈品來的
And it's a giveaway.
# 怎麼吃都行
I can feel free to enjoy it.
# 嗯~
Um~
# 你看這個楊梅
Have a look at the bayberries!
# 這個是
This is,
# 這個是比較大的楊梅啦
this is a relatively bigger bayberry.
# 還沒熟 null
It's still green.
# 還 差一點點就熟啦
It's almost ripe. It needs, only a tiny little bit of time.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個
These are,
# 這個熟啦
these are ripe now.
# 這樣子是 全紅的
This one is, completely red.
# 還可以哦 味道 很有楊梅味
It's not bad, the taste, a rich flavour of bayberries.
# 在樹在摘的比較新鮮
They're rather fresh as they're picked directly from the tree.
# 上樹上再摘幾個 樹頂上的比較好
Let me climb to the top of the tree and pick some there. The better ones are at the top of the tree.
# 哎呀 在這裡有一個那麼大 那麼大條的人在這裡 (註︰「一條人」是量詞的固意誤用以將人動物化，英語沒有量詞，所以改為把「人」物種化，藉以弱化「人」的概念)
Aya! Here is such a big, such a big human is here.
# 等會等會
A moment, a moment!
# 等一下你要 等你要把我搞下去
You need to, you need to take me down in a while.
# 你看這個兩個
Look at these two!
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 可以喲
Not bad!
# 這個楊梅 長大了 它就不酸啦 沒那麼酸
The bayberries are not sour, not that sour, when they grow up.
# 那裡有好大的
There's a very big one!
# 哎呀 這個
Aya! This is,
# 這個太大啦
this is simply too big!
# 你看
Look!
# 這個
This is,
# 又大又紅
big and red.
# 肯定很好吃
It must taste very good!
# 嗯~
Um~
# 等下我拿個桶來 裝點回去吃
I'm gonna get a bucket, and bring some back home.
# 拿來曬那個
I can dry them under the sun, and you know,
# 曬那個楊梅乾
and make some dried bayberries.
# 我來摘點那個李子 那個李子熟啦
Let's pick some plums. The plums are ripe now.
# 三華李
Sanhua plums
# 哇 這裡 好多啊 這裡
Wa! Here, so many here!
# 又大又紅
Big and red!
# 哇
Wa!
# 你看
Look!
# 這個
This is,
# 夠大吧
big, isn't it?
# 搓兩下
Rub it
# 先吃再說
Let me finish it first.
# 全是紅的
It's all red.
# 你看這裡
Have a look here!
# 這個
This is,
# 多紅啊 這個
really red, this one.
# 摘的話要摘大的
Pick only the big ones.
# 專門桃 大的摘
Look for the big ones, and pick only the big ones.
# 很靚的 這個三華李
They're so beautiful, these Sanhua plums.
# 差點就掉
They almost fell.
# 差點就掉到溝裡面去了
They almost fell into the pit.
# 把它摘掉
Let me pick them.
# 要不然一下兩的話掉到溝裡面去就麻煩啦
Otherwise it would be too bad if they all fall into the pit when the rain comes.
# 你看這些 這都是超級大 這些
Have a look at these! They're super big, all these.
# 夠大
It's so big.
# 把這個
Let me,
# 大的摘掉
pick the big ones.
# 你看這種
Have a look at this one.
# 這種就很好吃的
This type is really tastey.
# 你看這個
Have a look at this one!
# 擦一下
Rub it
# 反光
Shiny!
# 這個
These plums,
# 不要太熟 太熟了就只有甜味啦
shouldn't be too ripe. There's only sweetness if they're too ripe.
# 就像這樣酸酸甜甜的
Now it's like sweet and sour.
# 而且很脆
And it's really crunchy.
# 你看
Look!
# 三十稍就摘了那麼多
I've picked so many in just thirty seconds.
# 一樹都是
They're all over the trees.
# 你看這一個 那麼大這個
Have a look at this one! This one is so big!
# 好大的 這個
It's really big, this one.
# 搞得我直接說客家了
So big that it makes me speak in Hakka dialect right away.
# 看下好不好吃 嘗一下
Let me see if it's tasty. I have a try.
# 嗯
Um~
# 最少一兩
It weighs at least half a kilogram.
# 血紅色的
It's bloody red.
# 你看這個桃子 那麼小的樹都長那麼多個出來
Have a look at the peaches. It's such a small tree but there are so many peaches.
# 肯定在想 不長那麼多個出來的話
It must be thinking, that its owner would chop it down,
# 它的主人肯定把它砍掉
if it has any less peaches.
# 所以你看
So, you see!
# 長了幾個又大又紅的
It has some big and red ones.
# 你別看它那麼小
Don't judge it by its small size.
# 但是很甜的哦
It's really sweet, you know.
# 果 那個肉甜
The fruit, I mean the pulp is sweet.
# 這毛太多啦
It's too furry.
# 好多啊 你看
A lot! Look!
# 那麼小的樹長幾十個出來
There are dozens of them in such a small tree.
# 那個裡面還有 我們看一下
There are more inside. Let's take a look!
# 你看 這裡還有一個小西瓜
Look! Here's also a tiny watermelon.
# 還沒熟哦
It's not yet ripe.
# 那麼一點點
It's just a tiny little one.
# 就一個啊 那麼多棵西瓜樹
Just one? Here are so many watermelon trees.
# 就長了一個
That's the only one.
# 你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's one!
# 那麼大顆 這個
It's so big, this one.
# 好紅啊 這個
It's so red, this one.
# 它的果肉好好吃啊
Its pulp is really tasty.
# 把它的皮削掉
Peal it,
# 很好吃的
and it's really tasty.
# 忘記帶刀了
I've left my knife behind.
# 你看
Look!
# 肉都可以
The pulp can be,
# 肉都快紅啦
the pulp is turning red.
# 快熟了是吧
It's almost ripe, isn't it?
# 嗯
Um!
# 剛剛好 剛剛好
Just right, just right.
# 你看這種桃子 好紅啊
Look! These peaches, they're so red.
# 白裡透紅
Rosy white,
# 粉紅
or pink.
# 又掉了一個小的 這個
Another one drops down, this one.
# 有點
It's a bit,
# 本來
originally,
# 應該是
it should be,
# 跟鷹嘴桃有點像 但是又不是鷹嘴桃
it should look a bit like an acorn peach, but it's not really an acorn peach.
# 剝都剝不開
I can't crack it open.
# 你看 這個肉
Look! The pulp,
# 這個肉很好吃的
the pulp is really tasty.
# 沒辦法 只能這樣咬了
I can only just bite, no other choices.
# 你看 這個李子
Look! These plums,
# 還不是很紅
are still not really that red.
# 但是這個可以吃的 你看這個 這個就很靚的 這個
But this one is already edible. Have a look at this one! This one is really beautiful, this one.
# 摘這個的時候有一點紅就可以啦 不用太紅
They can be picked when they're only a bit red. They don't need to be too red.
# 這個拿回去 一兩天就把它廿 這個很好吃的
Take them back, I can finish them in a day or two. They're really tasty.
# 那麼大
It's so big!
# 你看
Look!
# 很靚哦
Beautiful, aren't they?
# 剛好兄弟 兄弟他們也過來啦
Just now our buddies, our buddies are here.
# 讓他們幫忙裝 等一下一人 一人拿兩箱
I let them help with the packing. Each, each of them is gonna carry two.
# 多的 多的拿回去 送兄弟姐妹
The extra, the extra, will be given to our brothers and sisters,
# 叔叔阿姨
uncles and aunties,
# 大哥大妹
sirs and madams.
# 應該可能再一箱 剛剛好 (註︰這句沒看懂，照字面翻譯吧)
I think each of them can have one more box, perfect!